地         球         脉         动   I I
世界上超过八千米的山峰
There are only fourteen peaks in the world
屈指可数
that rise to over 8000 metres.
它们全部位于喜马拉雅地区
All of them are here, in the Himalayas.
在极端低温与暴风雪的洗礼下
Lethally cold, scoured by gales and blizzards,
这些山脉成为地球上生存条件最苛刻的地区
these mountains are among the most hostile places on Earth.
然而  仍有动物能够生活在这里
Yet, a few special animals manage to live here.
雪豹
Snow leopards.
与所有高山生物相同
Like all creatures of the high mountains,
为了生存  他们必须从体型和行为上
they have had to adapt both their body and their behaviour
充分适应环境
in order to survive.
极高海拔之上的生存
Life at extreme altitude
塑造出了这个星球上最顽强的动物
has shaped some of the toughest animals on the planet.
山        脉
阿拉伯半岛上的山地被阳光炙烤得发烫
The sunbaked mountains of the Arabian Peninsula.
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
它们的海拔也许只是喜马拉雅山脉的零头
They may only be a fraction of the height of the Himalayas,
但却异常险峻
but they are still so dizzyingly steep
很多地方几乎无法立足
that in many places it's almost impossible to get a foothold.
而努比亚羱羊还是栖息于此
Yet Nubian ibex have made this their home.
羱羊选择在最陡峭的绝壁上养育幼仔
The ibex choose the steepest cliffs to raise their young,
环境安全  没有天敌
in safety, beyond the reach of predators.
在生活在这里也要付出代价
But living in this sanctuary comes with a cost.
山崖过于陡峭
These nursery slopes are so steep,
几乎没有任何积水
there is almost no standing water up here.
为了饮水  羱羊必须下到
So to drink, an ibex family must descend into the valley...
三百米下的峡谷之中
...1,000 feet below.
母羊选出一条最安全的下山路径
The mothers pick out the safest way down.
四只柔软的分趾蹄胜过最好用的登山鞋
With soft cloven hooves that grip better than any climbing shoe,
让他们成为最高超的登山者
they are the most accomplished mountaineers.
但新生的雏羊还在蹒跚学步
But the newborn kids are still having to find their feet.
这是他们第一次下山
This is their first descent.
一次失蹄就可能一命呜呼
One mistake could make it their last.
跟着成年羱羊  小羊们终于到达山谷
Following the adults, the kids finally reach the valley.
但回到平地上  他们就很容易遭到攻击
But once on level ground, they're vulnerable.
赤狐埋伏许久了
Red foxes lie in wait.
一有危险迹象
At the first sign of danger,
羱羊幼仔便本能地奔回陡坡
the young ibex instinctively run back to steeper ground.
但爬上这块突出的岩石可能是个错误
But heading for this particular rocky outcrop could be a mistake.
这有九米高
It's a 30-foot drop.
赤狐把它们困住了
The fox has them trapped...
或者看起来是这样
or so it seems.
这正是羱羊与生俱来的本领
This is what ibex were born to do.
四散而逃的羊群让赤狐难以选择目标
Scattering makes it hard for the fox to pick a target.
显然它也无法追上峭壁
And it certainly can't follow them up here.
只能等待某只羱羊失蹄跌落
All it can do is wait for one to slip and fall.
但这些小羊学得很快
But these youngsters are fast learners,
现在几乎可以和双亲一样如履平地了
and they're now almost as sure-footed as their parents.
赤狐只能去别处觅食
The fox will have to find its meal elsewhere.
今天还真不是个好日子
It's just not been a good day.
小羱羊终于喝上水了
Now, at last, the young ibex can drink.
但很快他们又得
But they'll soon need to
回到峭壁上的安全区域
return to the safety of the sheer cliffs.
在峭壁上行走固然很难
Mastering precipitous terrain is always challenging,
但对于高山动物而言
but there are more fundamental problems
还有更根本的难题
for life in the mountains.
阿尔卑斯山脉  欧洲最高的山峰
The Alps. Europe's highest peaks.
时至冬季  食物极度匮乏
It's winter, and food is desperately short.
金雕不得不花费整个白天
A golden eagle has to spend every daylight hour
俯视山坡  寻找食物
scanning the slopes for something, somewhere, to eat.
长达两米的翼展让她
Her seven-foot wingspan allows her to glide effortlessly
一天可以轻松滑翔一百六十公里
for 100 miles in a single day.
非凡的视力
Her extraordinary eyes
让她可以看到三公里外的猎物
enable her to spot prey from two miles away.
但她并非这里唯一的觅食者
But she is not the only one who's looking for food.
一旦发现良机  必须快速行动
When she spots a chance, she must move fast.
她能以三百二十公里的时速俯冲而下
She can dive at 200 miles an hour.
只有游隼能飞得更快
Only a peregrine is faster.
在冬季  即使鹰类也几乎完全仰赖腐尸度日
During winter, even eagles rely almost entirely on carrion.
这是一只死去的狐狸
It's a dead fox,
这顿美餐能让她支撑数日
and it could sustain her for days.
其它食腐者只能等着了
Other scavengers must defer.
饥饿的乌鸦很快重新鼓起勇气
The hungry crows soon regain their courage.
他们想尽办法  试图分一杯羹
They'll try any trick to steal a morsel.
顽固地令人厌烦
And they are annoyingly persistent.
但这群乌鸦是她最不需要担心的
But this mob are the least of her worries.
一只更大的金雕抢走了食物
A bigger eagle takes control.
但这顿美餐太过重要  不能轻易放弃
But this kill is too important to give up.
必须奋起一搏
So she must fight.
她暂时抢回了尸体
For the moment, she's won the carcass back.
但这样的猎物会引来方圆数公里内所有的鹰
But a kill like this will attract every eagle for miles around.
最终依然是最强者赢得大部分食物
As ever, the strongest wins the lion's share.
抢不到那具尸体
Unable to defend the carcass any longer,
第一只雕只能继续它的觅食之旅
the first eagle must now continue its search.
也许下一次饱餐就是数日之后的事情了
It may be many days before she feeds again.
只有最具竞争力的生物
Only the most competitive
才能在山脉的寒冬中存活下来
will survive the perils of the mountain winter.
一场雪崩
An avalanche.
十万吨积雪
100,000 tonnes of snow
以一百三十公里的时速席卷而下
travelling at 80 miles an hour,
足以粉碎沿途的一切
capable of smashing everything in its path.
北美洲的山脉
The mountains of North America
每年要发生数千起雪崩
are hit by thousands of avalanches every year.
然而有一种动物整个冬季
Yet one animal spends the whole winter slumbering
都在这些极易发生雪崩的山坡上冬眠
within the snow on these avalanche-prone slopes.
待春天来临  它们就出洞了
And when spring comes, they emerge.
在这些山脉中
All across these mountains,
灰熊将巢筑在背风坡厚厚的积雪之下
grizzly bears make their winter dens
海拔高达三千米
10,000 feet up in the deep snow of leeward slopes.
他们在隆冬半梦半醒之际
And while they were half-asleep in the depths of winter,
产下幼崽
their young were born.
现在这些熊宝宝正迈出他们
Now these cubs are taking their first steps
走向外界的第一步
into the outside world.
熊妈妈带着三只幼崽
This mother is leading her three youngsters
去找东西吃
to a place where they can find food.
他们得尽快下山
They need to descend as quickly as possible.
雪崩肆虐后的残骸清楚地表明
The debris from an avalanche is clear evidence
这片山坡仍然非常不稳定
that this slope is still dangerously unstable.
此地不宜久留
This is not a place to dawdle.
他们继续前行还有另一个原因
And they have another reason to keep moving.
在巢里呆了五个月后
After five months in the den,
这些灰熊饿得正慌
these bears are very hungry.
这片山峰之间冬眠的灰熊
Bears that have hibernated throughout these peaks
现在都下山了  那里的春天来得更早
now all descend to the valleys, where spring comes earliest.
落基山脉的季节变换迅速而突然
In the Rockies, seasonal change is swift and dramatic.
几天时间内
In just a few days,
白雪皑皑的山脉便会绿意盎然
the slopes turn from white to green.
几周前还深埋在冰天雪地里的牧场
Meadows that only a few weeks ago were buried beneath the snow
现在生机勃勃
are now full of life.
但山峦之间  好时光不会太久
But in these mountains, the good times will not last long.
所以灰熊必须尽快进食
So the bears must feed as fast as they can.
夏季的几个月里
During the summer months,
一只成年灰熊靠吃植物能长一百八十公斤
an adult can put on 180 kilos gorging on plants
要是能再...
and, if they can catch them...
逮几只土拨鼠就更好了
a marmot or two.
但现在灰熊们还有其他事情要做
But just now, the bears have something else on their minds.
天气转暖
It's becoming warmer,
灰熊急切地想脱下它们厚重的冬衣
and the bears are keen to shed their thick winter coats.
母熊给小熊们做了示范
Mothers show the cubs what to do about this.
他们很快就学会了
They'll soon catch on.
有一些树似乎特别适合搓背
Some trees, it seems, are particularly suitable for rubbing.
熊们都有自己的偏好
Bears have their favourites
他们会长途跋涉  去找喜欢的树
and will travel long distances to visit them.
身上有些痒  急需挠一挠
Some itches just have to be scratched.
这个山谷中大约有三十只熊
There are now around 30 bears in this one valley.
每只熊摩擦时都会留下易于辨认的独特气味
As they rub, each leaves an individual and recognisable scent.
所以树上很快会留有附近灰熊的气味
So the tree soon carries a list of who's around,
或许可以避免个体之间的争斗
which might help individuals to avoid a fight.
为了更好地散布自己的气味
To best spread their scent,
他们得用后背好好地蹭一蹭
they really have to put their back into it.
但是夏天很短暂
But summer is short.
痒痒挠满意之后
Itches satisfactorily scratched,
是时候该进食了
it's time to eat.
几个月后
In a couple of months,
他们就要回自己的窝里冬眠
they will have to return to their dens to hibernate,
所以现在必须尽可能地增重
so now they must put on as much weight as they can.
山里的冬天来得迅猛
Winter in the mountains returns fast and hits hard.
落基山脉地区的温度会降至零下五十四度
Temperatures in the Rockies will drop to -54 degrees,
以至于空气中的水分
so cold that moisture in the air
会直接凝结成冰晶  俗称钻石尘
freezes into tiny crystals called diamond dust.
山猫是少数冬天还在活动的捕猎者
This bobcat is one of the few hunters to remain active in winter.
他领地内的大多数猎物都
Most of his prey is now hidden beneath the snow
隐藏在茫茫大雪之下
that covers his entire territory.
他通过辨认极其微弱的声音来捕捉猎物
He hunts by listening for the faintest sound of movement.
为了避免踩雪的脚步声暴露行踪
And to prevent crunching footsteps from revealing his presence,
他用岩石当落脚点
he uses boulders as stepping stones.
逮住一只老鼠
A mouse.
但这远远不够
But one is not enough.
积雪越深越难发现猎物
The deeper the snow, the harder it is to detect prey,
努力捕食却往往空手而归
and the rewards for the effort can be disappointing.
这么说毫不夸张
To say the least.
深冬时节积雪实在太深
By midwinter, the snow is so deep
山猫被迫离开他们的领地
that bobcats are forced to leave their territories
寻找更易于捕捉的猎物
to try and find easier hunting.
但这只山猫运气不错
And this bobcat may be in luck.
因为这个山谷得自然之眷顾
For this particular valley is blessed.
这条河永不结冰
A river here never freezes.
火山温泉带来的热量
It's fed by a volcanic hot spring
使河水升温
that heats these waters
比周围空气的温度高了五十余度
to 50 degrees warmer than the surrounding air.
各种饥肠辘辘的动物来此觅食
Hungry animals of all kinds come here to feed.
到了冬天
Throughout the winter,
对于那些老道的捕猎者而言
the river is full of food
河里满是食物
for those who know how to catch it.
在这里连土狼都学会了捕鱼
Here, even the coyotes have become fishermen.
但是捕鱼对山猫来说很难
But hunting is hard for a cat
因为他们讨厌下水
that's not used to getting its feet wet.
所以他必须谨慎选择目标
So he must choose his target with care.
白颊鸭来了
Goldeneye ducks.
但他能够靠近到扑得着吗
But can he get close enough to pounce?
也许对岸的机会更大点
Perhaps he'll have more luck on the other side.
河里的热气温暖了周围的树林
Here, steam from the river warms the surrounding trees,
所以林子里可能有猎物
so up in the branches, there could be prey.
前提是他能爬得上去
If only he could get to it.
这有六米高
It's 20 feet up.
最终收获一只松鼠
At last... a squirrel.
不是很多  但是足以支撑他继续捕食
Not much, but enough to keep him going.
想要渡过山里的冬天需要坚韧不拔的意志
To survive a winter in these mountains takes tenacity,
而山猫是其中的佼佼者
and bobcats have that in abundance.
这是一座赤道雪山
Snow on the equator.
与落基山脉不同  这里的山脉
Unlike the Rockies, in these mountains
没有明显的四季
there are no marked seasons.
这是非洲的肯尼亚山
This is Africa's Mount Kenya.
海拔超过五千米
It's 17,000 feet high,
峰顶温度比周围的热带草原
which makes its summit some 30 degrees colder
低三十度左右
than the surrounding savanna.
巨型石南  半边莲和千里光
Giant heathers, lobelias and groundsel
生长在山顶斜坡上
grow on its upper slopes.
它们在炎炎烈日下茁壮成长
They all thrive in the tropical sun.
毕竟赤道每天都是夏天
After all, every day is summer.
但一旦太阳下山
But once the sun sets,
每个夜晚都像冬天般寒冷
every night becomes as bitterly cold as winter.
气温降到零下五度
The temperature drops to five degrees below freezing,
山坡变成了冰雪花园
turning the mountainside into a garden of ice.
一切都冻结了
Everything freezes,
但是木本千里光有办法保护自己
but the cabbage groundsels have a way of protecting themselves.
它们合起革质叶片形成一道保温层
They close up their leathery leaves to form an insulating blanket
以保护中心脆弱的蓓蕾
that shields their vulnerable central bud.
寒夜将尽
Night comes to an end...
阳光回归大地
...and the sunshine returns.
木本千里光舒展它们的叶子
The groundsels spread their leaves wide
再一次沐浴在阳光之中
to bask in the sunshine once again.
安第斯山脉的黎明来到
Dawn in the High Andes.
在这里  升起的朝阳同样解放了
Here too, the rising sun brings rapid relief
生活在火山山峰之间的动物
to animals living amongst these volcanic peaks.
山兔鼠早早起来
Mountain viscacha are up early
抢占最佳位置  享受第一缕阳光
to claim the best places to catch the sun's first rays.
对于其他的动物  太阳更加受到欢迎
For others up here, the sunrise is even more welcome.
这里的海拔超过四千米
At over 14,000 feet,
是世界上海拔最高的火烈鸟栖息地
this is the highest flamingo colony in the world.
这里的夜晚非常寒冷
At night, it gets so cold
连盐水湖都会结冰
that even this salty water freezes over.
这些火烈鸟就被冻在了冰里
And now the flamingos are trapped in the ice.
终于太阳晒薄了冰面
Eventually, the sun thins the ice,
但是火烈鸟仍然需要努力冲破冰层
but it's still a struggle for the flamingos to break free.
走在薄冰上总是危机四伏
Walking on thin ice is always risky.
而且当你踩着高跷的时候
And it's hard to retain one's dignity...
哪还顾得上体面和优雅
...especially when you're wearing stilts.
海拔如此之高
At these altitudes,
太阳的热力很快从救星变成了威胁
the sun's power can quickly turn from salvation to threat.
由于大气稀薄
The atmosphere is so thin,
无法阻挡紫外线的辐射
there is very little protection from ultraviolet radiation.
上午十点钟在开阔地带逗留就已经十分危险
By mid-morning, it's risky to linger out in the open.
鼠兔被迫寻找阴凉处避暑
The viscacha are forced to head for the shade.
而湖面上则无处可藏
Out on the lake, there is nowhere to hide.
盐湖的白色盐层反射着
The white crust of the soda lake
太阳的光芒
reflects the sun's glare
增强了紫外线的杀伤力
and increases the impact of its ultraviolet rays.
正午时分
By midday,
裸露的人类肌肤四分钟内就会被晒伤
uncovered human skin will burn in four minutes.
但这似乎无法妨碍到火烈鸟
But this doesn't seem to bother the flamingos.
事实上  它们正在列队游行
In fact, they are on parade.
在繁殖季节
During the breeding season,
即便在一天中最热的时刻
the flamingos perform these peculiar courtship dances
火烈鸟也在不停表演着奇异的求爱舞蹈
even through the hottest time of the day.
他们求爱心切  甚至没时间停下来进食
They are so eager, they don't even pause to feed.
尽管求爱规则让人摸不着头脑
The rules are something of a mystery
但在跳了一个月之后
but, after a month of dancing,
所有的鸟儿都配对成功
all the birds will have paired off
并准备开始交配
and will be getting ready to mate.
高山之上  很少有其他动物来打扰火烈鸟
Up here, there are few other creatures to bother the flamingos,
从另一方面讲  也少有其他动物
but then, few other creatures
能够忍受这样的生活条件
could even tolerate these conditions.
对于耐力极佳的动物而言
So for animals that have the endurance,
深山堪称生存的圣殿
mountains can be sanctuaries.
那些在我们看来
But rocky peaks which to us, perhaps,
似乎象征着永恒的岩石山峰
seem a symbol of permanence,
其实要脆弱得多
are more fragile than they appear.
如今在阿尔卑斯山
Today in the Alps,
人类的侵犯甚至影响到顶峰的环境状况
human encroachment is changing even the highest summits.
在落基山脉
In the Rockies,
升高的气温缩短了冬眠的时间
rising temperatures are shortening winter hibernation
也阻碍了食料植物的生长
and stifling the growth of valuable food plants.
在安第斯山脉  一些冰川
And in the Andes, some glaciers
在短短三十年内面积减少了百分之五十
have shrunk by 50% in just 30 years.
如今  甚至连喜马拉雅山脉都变得十分脆弱
Even the Himalayas are now vulnerable.
这里汇集着大多数世上最高的山峰
With most of the world's tallest peaks
占地面积八十六万平方公里
and covering a third of a million square miles,
是世界上最大的山脉
this is the greatest mountain range of all.
而这里气温升高的速度
And here, temperatures are now rising
快于全球平均水平
faster than the global average.
雪线向山峰处退去
As the snow line retreats further and further up these peaks,
野生动植物的生存空间日益减少
there is less and less space for wildlife,
恶化的条件威胁着
and that is a challenge
一种美丽山地动物的生存
for one of the most majestic of all mountain creatures.
雪豹
The snow leopard.
由于行踪隐蔽  雪豹的生活细节一直是个谜
Seldom seen, the detail of their lives has long been a mystery,
但现在  借助最先进的远程摄像技术
but now, at last, helped by the latest remote-camera technology,
我们终于能够近距离观察他们
we are getting closer to them than ever before.
雪豹数量稀少
They are very rare,
百平方公里内只有四只
only about four of them in 40 square miles.
只是因为猎物数量不足以维系更多的生命
There is simply not enough prey to sustain more.
雪豹是独居动物
They live solitary lives.
尽管如此  他们仍能很好地掌握
Nonetheless, they are well aware of the presence
邻居们的存在和动向
and the movements of their neighbours,
因为他们会在几个特殊地点给对方留下信息
because they leave messages in a few special places.
像这样用脸颊摩擦特定的岩石
They rub particular rocks with their cheeks
再喷射上自己的尿液
and then spray them with urine.
两种味道创造出了独一无二的签名
The two perfumes create a unique signature.
尽管没有直接看到彼此
Any other leopard can know
雪豹也能判断出
which of its neighbours passed this way,
是哪位邻居曾经到此一游
without ever making direct contact.
有些时候雪豹们必须聚到一起
But there are times when snow leopards must come together,
而场面通常都很暴力
and the event is often violent.
一只成年雌雪豹和她的女儿
An adult female and her daughter.
雌雪豹花费了两年时间哺育幼崽
She has devoted the last two years to raising her cub
很快  幼崽就要断奶了
and very soon, it will be weaned.
目前  幼崽依旧完全依靠自己的母亲
For now, the cub is still entirely dependent on its mother.
但这样长时间的共处会引发问题
But staying together as long as this could cause problems.
雌雪豹此时又到了发情期
The female is now in heat again,
雄雪豹只需闻到她的信号便会知晓
and any male that smells her signature will know that.
从此刻起  雌雪豹幼崽的生命陷入了危机
From this moment on, her cub's life is at risk.
雄雪豹会杀死非亲生的幼崽
Males kill cubs that are not their own.
但雌雪豹此时正被体内无法控制的欲望驱使着
But the mother is now driven by an urge that she cannot control.
她让雄雪豹知道了她的确切位置
She lets the males know exactly where she is.
从这片高地  她的声音可以传遍方圆数公里
From up here, she can be heard for miles around.
一只年轻雄雪豹在荒野中出现
A young male emerges from the wilderness,
迫切地想要找到雌雪豹
eager to find her.
雪豹们很少碰面
Snow leopards meet so infrequently
以致整个场面充斥着不确定和紧张的气氛
that there is uncertainty and tension.
然而更糟的还在后面
And it's about to get worse.
另一只体型更为健壮的雄雪豹也来了
Another, bigger male has arrived.
雌雪豹和幼崽被困在两个竞争对手之间
The mother and cub are trapped between the rivals.
幼崽命在旦夕
The cub is now in danger.
母亲必须尽快行动
Mother must act fast.
为了转移雄雪豹对幼崽的注意力
To divert the males' attention from her cub,
她顺从地滚动着身体
she rolls over submissively.
雄雪豹的注意力都集中在了雌雪豹身上
With the males fixed on the female,
幼崽得以借此机会脱身
the cub has a chance to escape.
两只雄雪豹从两侧接近雌雪豹
The males close in on the mother from both sides,
渴望将其占为己有
keen to claim her for their own.
决斗在所难免
A fight is inevitable.
雌雪豹试图逃跑并保护她的幼崽
The female moves to escape and protect her cub.
但健硕的雄雪豹紧跟着她
But the big male follows her.
在没有交配前  雄雪豹是不会放她走的
He will not let her leave until he has mated with her.
雄雪豹走后  雌雪豹终于与幼崽重聚
With the males gone, the female is at last reunited with her cub.
但她不幸受了伤
But she has been injured.
多亏了她的妈妈  幼崽才能活下来
The cub, however, is alive, thanks to its mother.
在雌雪豹伤口痊愈之前  她已无法捕猎
Until her injury heals, she won't be able to hunt.
山地动物就这样挣扎在存活的边缘
Mountain animals survive on the very edge of existence.
雌雪豹和幼崽从此消失不见
Mother and cub were not seen again.
直到一个月后  在高高的山脊上
Until over a month later, high on a ridge,
远程摄像机捕捉到了
a remote camera was triggered.
雌雪豹的身影
The female cat.
她已不再跛足而行  却形单影只
She's no longer limping, but she's now alone.
雌雪豹离开后一个小时
Then, an hour after the female has left,
摄像机再次启动
the camera is triggered again.
是幼崽
It's her cub,
开始了迈向成年和独立的第一步
taking her first steps towards adulthood and independence.
幼崽大概很少有机会与母亲重逢了
She is unlikely to see her mother again.
但不时地
But every now and then,
他们会通过在岩石上留下的信息
they will be reunited through the messages they leave
间接地团聚
on the marking rocks.
幼崽虽被母亲成功养大
Her mother has succeeded in raising her,
但前方的生存之路仍充满荆棘
but life ahead will be challenging,
而她几乎全部要独自面对
and she will spend nearly all of it alone.
只有最顽强的动物
Only the toughest can survive
才能在世界最高屋脊上
among the savage beauty
这片美丽的蛮夷之地存活
of the world's highest mountains.
下一集
Next time...
我们到世界各地探索丛林
we explore the world's jungles.
地球上充满惊喜和创造力无与伦比的地方
Places of surprise and invention unrivalled on Earth...
那里的生存之战最为激烈
...where the battle for survival is at its most intense.